Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today
we're going to be going through
how to balance redox reactions,
specifically in basic solutions.
So whenever it comes to trying to balance
these in basic solutions, these can be
some of the most complex redox reactions.
Just being that it involves an extra
step, being that we're in solution,
right, so it should be in water.
But we're going to be adding that
base component, maybe something like
sodium hydroxide, or like barium
hydroxide, or some kind of strong base.
That's changing the pH of the
solution, therefore helping
the electrons be transferred.
And that's going into a little
bit more detail than what we need.
So we're going to go through
exactly how we're going to do
these and what do these look like.
So typically whenever we have these
kinds of reactions, you're going to
see an imbalance of charge on the
left and the right hand side of the
problem, meaning that no matter how
many coefficients you add, it's not
going to generally fix, um, what that
charges, um, in any simple means.
So what we're going to have to do is
add waters and hydroxides and different
things to it in order to balance it.
And the whole reason for this
is because of it being an
oxidation and reduction reaction.
We're going to be doing that
whole entire LEO goes GER, right?
Thinking of our growling lion.
So Leo, meaning loss of electrons.
And the other thing going
through gaining electrons.
So we're going to go through the
exact steps of how to do this.
And then at the end of the
problem, I'll show you the
entire summary of all of them.
So let's go through and see what
kind of problem this would look like.
This kind of problem would
look like something like this.
So we would have complete and balance the
following equation in a basic solution.
Using the half reaction method.
So, as you can see, we have, uh,
NO2 being added to aluminum to make
ammonia, and then aluminum hydroxide.
So, with this one, you can see
that there is a charge imbalance.
There's charges on different species.
Things don't quite match up.
Um, so, I'm also asking can you label
the oxidizing and reducing agent as well?
Just to practice the full,
the cold, complete picture.
Now keep in mind this could be shown in
a couple different ways in a problem.
It could be listed out in
the problem like this above.
Sometimes you might have it
where it says in a basic medium.
This is just the same idea of a solution.
Um, it's just another way
of writing the same idea.
Um, the other way too is that sometimes
you'll see it where it says basic
over the reaction arrow as well.
There's three different ways to kind of
try to give you that hint of hey, you
need to do the half reaction method in
order to balance this in a basic medium.
So let's go through our steps.
And we're going to be following
our general set of rules for how
to label an oxidation number.
So when we have, let's say, the following
formula like we had before, we're going
to be going through each of the different
following rules to try to help guide us.
And a lot of these is kind of
like putting them to memory.
So for example, like fluorine
is always negative one.
Oxygen is generally negative two
hydrogen is generally plus one.
Um, but there are some little
exceptions as well, so we're
gonna try to remember all of them.
So, let's say for the first one,
right, the first thing is keeping
in mind that the sum of the
oxidation numbers must be equal to
the charge of whatever the ion is.
So we see we have this negative
1, so that must mean the entire
thing must be equal to negative 1.
So, we know that every oxygen
is equivalent to negative 2.
So the way that we'll end up kind of
writing these is I write like a little,
like, little T for myself to do some math.
So if I have two oxygens, each
one's negative two, that means the
total on that side is negative four.
So in order for it to equal that
negative one, that must mean that
nitrogen has to be positive three
in order to make that math work out.
Now we'll move over to our aluminum,
and with that one, right, it's one of
those elements that's completely by
itself, right, so it's its natural form.
So whenever we have something by itself,
that means it's going to be a zero.
Now we'll move over to the next
one, and we can see that whenever
hydrogen is bound to a nonmetal, It's
going to have a plus one, so we can
kind of do the same little T here.
So we know we have three of them, so
that means overall it's plus three.
So what we need to do in order to balance
that is nitrogen needs to be minus three.
So we have that one.
Now with this one, the aluminum
hydroxide, this one's a little bit
trickier, um, being that we kind of have
a polyatomic bound to this, and then
we also have the overall charge too.
So we got to kind of keep
everything in mind while doing this.
So hydroxide in its own
right is negative one.
So the way we can kind of view this thing
is being that there's four hydroxides.
Right, so each one of them is negative
1, um, meaning that will tell us
that aluminum is going to have a
positive 3, being that every single
hydroxide OH is going to be negative 1.
If we want to go further in trying
to label everything, we can.
Right, keep in mind hydrogen is plus 1,
and being that a hydroxide is negative 1.
That must mean that each
oxygen is negative 2.
Alright, now the tough part is
labeling our oxidation reduction.
So we're looking for anything
that's changing charges going
from the left and the right.
One of those is that we can
see is the nitrogens, right?
We can see nitrogens going from plus
3 to negative 3, meaning it's becoming
more negative or it's gaining electrons.
So if you remember, er, right,
gaining electrons means reduced.
Now we're going to look for what's
being oxidized, so we're trying to
look for what's losing electrons.
And we can see that the aluminum
is going from 0 to plus 3.
So, therefore, it must be losing
three electrons in that process
based on what we have right now.
Okay.
So that is our oxidized.
All right.
So aluminum is being oxidized,
nitrogen is being reduced.
Now when it comes to labeling our first
question, which was what's the oxidizing
agent, what's the reducing agent.
Remember it's like an agent of chaos.
So it's something that causes
something causes the chaos.
So the oxidizing agent causes oxidation
being that these are these reactions
are in a are in a pair, right when
we kind of look at them, right?
So even though nitrogen is being reduced,
NO two is causing aluminum to be oxidized.
So the way that we're gonna look at this
is NO two is gonna be our oxidizing agent.
So it's the whole molecule
instead of just an element.
Therefore, when we look at
this, aluminum is causing ni
or nitrogen to be, uh, reduced.
So therefore, this is our reducing agent.
Okay, so now our next step, step
number two, is we're going to write
out our half reactions, which are
going to emphasize the oxidized and
the reduced parts of the reaction.
Now when you do these, you
could technically skip the
first step if you wanted to.
I really only would recommend it to
people who have a lot of practice.
Um, the big thing is that they have
to kind of match like the metals or
like whatever the, the other element
is in each one of them, like, for
example, like aluminum, you can
see on both sides of the oxides.
So, you know, those are
going to go together.
Same with the nitrogens.
Um, but it's usually good practice
to label them being that you have
to be able to label these on any
type of exam or quiz or homework.
So we're going to write the
half reaction for each one.
So we'll start with our oxidized, right?
We can see aluminum is turning
into aluminum, uh, hydroxide.
Right.
And we have that negative charge
on it and it has a minus on it.
All right.
And that's the big thing is
write down all your charges.
I can't tell you how many times I
actually make a mistake on these
because I forgot to write a charge.
So that's going to be the oxidized.
So we'll label that.
So we can remember that for later.
And then for nitrogen, right?
We know that's going
to be the reduced one.
So it's going to be N O two.
Aqueous is going to be turning into Uh,
and H3 and notice that I kind of almost
forgot my charge on the N8 and O2.
So like I said, write everything
down, it's really easy to do.
And this is our first step, right?
Pretty easy.
Now we're going to go
through our balancing.
So what we're going to do here is.
I'm going to just take one of these
and we'll kind of do it like step
by step and then we'll like kind
of do the fast, I'll show you like
the faster way to kind of remember
it, remember the entire balancing.
So we'll start with the aluminum
hydroxide, just being that's on top
here, no particular order, does not
matter which one you start with.
And then we'll do the NO2 next.
Okay, so let's go to our next
step and show how aluminum and 2
aluminum hydroxide will be balanced.
Okay, so step number three is we're
going to balance all other atoms, meaning
anything that's not hydrogen or oxygen.
Being that these are what's going
to be pertaining to our solution,
um, we will balance everything else.
So in this case, that would be
aluminum, being that's the only thing
here that's not oxygen or hydrogen.
And what you can see is, is
that we have one on each side.
So we're already done the
first, that, that third step.
That's pretty, that's pretty nice.
So, but the next step is when
the real challenge starts.
So we're, we're going to add water
in order to balance oxygen and then
H plus to balance the hydrogens.
So when we're kind of looking at this,
we, I got to examine it and see like,
Oh, Hey, did we have any imbalance?
of oxygen here.
And what you kind of will notice really
quickly is that, hey, we have those
four oxygens on the right hand side.
So what we need to do is add four
waters in response to that on the left.
So that balances our O's, but now we
have an imbalance of hydrogen, right?
We had four already on the right,
now we have eight on the left.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to add four hydrogens to the right
hand side in order to balance our O's.
All of the hydrogens.
So keep in mind you got to
add up all the pieces, right?
We had four, the four H's and then
the four that were in hydroxide.
Now our next step is
balancing our charges.
So we're going to add
electrons in order to do this.
So the thing I like to do is, is I like
to try to add up all my charges, like,
and kind of put a number underneath.
So like, for example, I have
four hydrogens, that's four plus.
On the aluminum hydroxide is a negative.
So that means the entire right hand
side, I have 3 Where on the left hand
side, I have an entire thing of 0.
So what we're going to do is, is
we're going to add 3 electrons
in order to balance that charge.
So we have 3 electrons on the
right hand side that I just added.
So what that does is that's
going to then cancel that.
So now what we're going to do is
we're going to do the same thing with
the other side of the half reaction.
So this is one of our answers.
We're not going to be
done even after that step.
We have a few more steps to go.
Alright, let's do the other half reaction.
All right, so we're going to do
the other half of this reaction,
but a little bit quicker.
So that way you can try to remember the
order for when you're going to do this.
So this is where I would recommend
maybe pausing the video and see if you
can do this half reaction on your own,
and then watch my explanation of it.
So the first thing, what are
we going to do is we're going
to balance the other atoms.
So what do we have is we have
nitrogen as our other atom in this
case, and it's already balanced.
So this is something that, oh, we
have a little bit, a little bit of
an easier problem for ourselves.
So now we're gonna balance the O's
so we can see we have two oxygens
on the left So what do we need to do
is we need to add two oxygens on the
right in the form of water All right.
Now what we're gonna do is we're
gonna balance our Hydrogens adding
by adding protons to this so I have
a total of Four so we have four
plus three hydrogens on the right.
So we have seven on the right hand
side So I need to add seven hydrogens
to the left in order to balance this.
Now, our next part is
balancing our charges.
So we have a total of six plus on the
left, and we have zero on the right.
So what do we need to do is we need
to balance that by adding electrons.
I'm going to move this over, and
we're going to add six electrons
to the right in order to do this.
And now we have our half
reaction for the reduction part.
Now, this is when we add them together
and try to cancel everything out.
Okay, this is the part where we now
multiply the half reactions to make the
electrons equal in both, so on both sides.
So notice how we have three electrons on
the top here, and on the bottom equation
we only have six, or we have six total.
So that doesn't show an equal transfer of
electrons, so generally what we have to
do is we have to usually multiply both of
them by each other's electrons to kind of
make them equal to each other, especially
if it's like 2 and 3, for example.
But in this case, being that we have 3 up
here, well, how do I make it equal to 6?
Is, that's a little bit easier,
is that we'll just multiply
the top by 2, and technically
I guess the bottom by 1, right?
We don't actually have to
do any math there, but Hey,
we'll just kind of mention it.
So we're going to multiply the top by two.
So when we do that, we're going
to be kind of redoing our math
here for all of our coefficients.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going
to move this guy down a little bit.
And what that means is
I'll have eight waters.
I'm going to have, uh, two aluminums
being that I'm multiplying everything.
Then I'll have two aluminum hydroxides.
And the big thing is here, what
it's doing is it's going to
keep everything charge balanced.
but it's also going to make it so
our electrons will cancel later,
which is our big thing, right?
Eight hydrogens.
And then we have our six electrons.
Okay.
So now we see our electrons are
equal, which means that when we
add these two equations together,
that the different pieces are going
to balance just like they should.
So that means we can kind of, uh,
well, I guess we could just kind of
keep that up here just to show our
work, but you know, that's where
you can kind of like cross that out.
And then we have our.
complete parts.
So let's go on to our next step.
Our next step is that we're going
to add our reactions together,
almost like a big math problem.
So we're going to add up all
the reactants, all the products.
But the big thing is that we're
going to cancel anything that's
matching on the left and the right,
almost like kind of like spectator
ions from net ionic equations.
So the first thing is like, just to
kind of point that out, it's like, you
can see that, Hey, we have matching
electrons on the left and right.
So they have to cancel.
That's a mandatory.
It won't, won't be correct without that.
So we can see that the 6
electrons do that on both sides.
Now, after that, we're going to cancel
anything that's kind of similar, right?
So we can see like water, for
example, is matching, but being
that we have an unequal amount,
right, we'll cancel the little one.
And so we have two waters canceling
two of the ones on the left.
So that means we have a
total of six now on the left.
We're going to do the same thing for
the hydrogens we add or added, right?
So we can see that, hey, we had.
7 on the left, we had 8 on the
right, so that's going to completely
get rid of all the hydrogens
except for 1 on the products.
Now we can add up everything that's left.
So what do we have, right?
We have, we want to make sure we're
very careful with adding everything.
It's very easy to miss something, right?
So we have 6 waters, the 2 aluminums.
Now NO two minus aqueous, and then we're
gonna add the two aluminum hydroxides,
and we wanna make sure that we get the
subscript order correct and then plus the
NH three and then plus the hydrogen ion.
Okay.
Now, one of the things that you might
be kind of saying to yourself is
like, well, is that entirely right?
I thought this was a.
Basic problem.
So this is notice that this is the exact
same process so far as an acidic medium.
But there's one last step, let's
show the last step for how to
balance this for a basic problem.
All right, our last step, being
that this isn't a basic solution,
what we now have to do is we have
to neutralize all hydrogen ions with
OH minus, being that that's the main
component of what makes a base, right?
Think of POH or anything that's basic when
we, when you learn about acids and bases.
So when we do this.
We have to add OH to both sides, but
it's all based on us trying to neutralize
that proton that's here in the products.
So being that we have one proton, what
does that mean is we're going to add one
hydroxide to both the left and the right.
We got to do it to both
sides, not just one.
So I'm going to add that above, right,
just to kind of show an example.
So I'm going to add that to both sides.
All right, now what does that mean?
Well, what happens when you have
H plus and OH minus together?
They combine and they make water, right?
They, they will make our water, right?
What sustains life.
So what does that mean is that
we have a water now on the left
instead of that H plus and OH
minus that we had there before.
So these will get converted.
Alright, so being that we have that
water, what does that mean is, well
remember, that whole entire thing with
the left and right, is we have to cancel
that with what's on the other side.
So when we do that, this one will go
away, and this number over here will turn
into a five, right, and it will change.
Now the hydroxide that I kind
of awkwardly wrote underneath.
That's gonna become a part of the problem.
So what are we gonna do is we're gonna
write down that we have five waters
now, and this will be our final answer
and we'll put our liquid symbol.
We have a hydroxide, right?
That's an aqueous.
Then our two aluminums combining with
our nitrite, NO two minus aqueous.
And that will turn it into uh,
two aluminums hydroxide minus
aqueous plus NH three aqueous.
So that is our final
answer to our problem.
So notice that that is
quite a bit of work, right?
And it looks insane.
So let's review all of our steps
so that way you can write them
down and you can try to do this on
your own for your future problems.
This is all of our steps for how to
balance a redox reaction in a basic
solution, but keep in mind I'm kind
of missing that last step here, so
let me scroll down here for a second.
So the first thing that we're
going to do is we're going to be
determining the oxidation numbers.
Now the reason for that is if you have to
label what's being reduced and oxidized,
you're going to need to label them.
That also helps you write out the half
reactions, especially if you're kind of
struggling to label them, or just to kind
of see the trends, then you definitely
want to be able to label those numbers.
Now for steps four through five,
you can combine them into one step.
Most textbooks that I read usually do.
So keep in mind that order.
Other atoms, then you do oxygen,
hydrogen, then electrons.
Other, oxygen, hydrogen, electrons.
Keep that order every single time.
You'll be able to get it right.
Now, from there, right, you're
gonna then multiply the half
reactions to cancel your electrons.
Um, that will allow you to
be able to add them together.
And then once you do that, your last
step, which sets this one, uh, different
from everything else, is like, when you
try to neutralize Which I guess it would
kind of help if I spelled that correctly.
I just noticed, um, so when you
neutralize, uh, any of these types
of problems, um, it's kind of, you're
cancelling out the protons with hydroxide.
So they cancel, right?
And that way it's going to make water.
So keep that in mind, right?
That's the trick to the basic one.
It's just one more step.
So this is kind of now officially
the hardest one, right?
So you kind of go from this unbalanced
form, right, where the charges are
not, not balanced between the different
ions, and then you can go to adding,
having hydroxide in the problem.
Um, you can see the basic
component, you can see water,
and then finally balancing it.
And it is a very, very long process.
So hope, good luck on all
these kind of problems.
I hope that this video helped you.
If this is your first time here,
please hit that like button, hit
the subscribe button, comment
if you have questions, right?
If anything is not clear or
you're trying to figure out best
resources to help you, please ask.
Or if you have suggestions for future
videos that you would love me to make that
try to help you in your chemistry class.
Um, and if you're one of my students, send
me a message, please reach out for help.
I will be, I would love
to do that for you.
Okay.
Thank you all.
I hope you have a wonderful
day and I'll see you all later.
Bye now.